<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of the Church of England from a general assembly of Covenanters in Scotland. Represented from their principles in oaths, and late acts of assemblies; compar'd with their practices in these last two years. Written in the year 1690. By a true son of the Church.</title>
            <author>True son of the church.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81600</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D179A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230519</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896399</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154141</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81600)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154141)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2401:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of the Church of England from a general assembly of Covenanters in Scotland. Represented from their principles in oaths, and late acts of assemblies; compar'd with their practices in these last two years. Written in the year 1690. By a true son of the Church.</title>
                  <author>True son of the church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for A. Baldwin in Warwick-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690 [i.e. 1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Wing (CD-ROM edition) reports date of publication as 1690 [i.e. 1698-1700]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Covenanters --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154141:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DANGER OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> FROM A GENERAL ASSEMBLY OF COVENANTERS IN SCOTLAND. Repreſented from their Principles in <hi>Oaths,</hi> and late <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Aſſemblies;</hi> compar'd with their Practices in theſe laſt two Years. Written in the Year 1690. <hi>By a True Son of the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>A. Baldwin</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:154141:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154141:2"/>
            <head>THE DANGER OF THE <hi>Church of England.</hi> From a General Aſſembly of COVENANTERS IN Scotland, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IN this Repreſentation of the danger of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters, we will make it appear, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That they are by their Principles, obliged not only in <hi>Scotland</hi> to keep up their Covenanted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154141:3"/> Presbytery to the Heighth, but alſo to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to introduce the ſame in the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland. Secondly,</hi> That they are at this time able to proſecute thoſe <hi>meaſures,</hi> which were then followed for <hi>that effect:</hi> And, <hi>thirdly,</hi> that they are moſt willing to trace the footſteps of <hi>their fathers,</hi> if the King interpoſe not his Authority for the protection of thoſe Epiſcopal Miniſters whom the Government hath not depriv'd in that Kingdom; and for a Legal Toleration, for the Exerciſe of the Reformed Religion, unto all peaceable Diſſenters.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe three. In the beginning of 1638. all the three Kingdoms enjoyed an Epiſcopal Government, and a Common Prayer, in the Church. In <hi>December</hi> 1638. the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Presbyterians took <hi>both</hi> away in <hi>Scotland,</hi> without the King's Authority. and in their having neither Biſhop nor Liturgy, they placed all the Reformation of the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. But they could not be ſecured of their being long without them, while the other two Kingdoms enjoyed them; and therefore when they Covenanted in <hi>Aug.</hi> 1639. in the very firſt Article of the Solemn League, in which they Swear <hi>to preſerve the Reformed Religion in the Church of</hi> Scotland, <hi>in Worſhip and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> they likewiſe bind themſelves by Oath <hi>to Reform the Kingdoms of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>in the ſame Points, and to bring the three Kingdoms to the neareſt conjunction and uniformity in both.</hi> And what this Reformation of Worſhip is, and by what Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it is to be directed, which they vow to preſerve among themſelves, and to introduce among
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154141:3"/> us, we cannot be ignorant, if we read the ſecond Article of their Covenant, where they Swear un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an <hi>Extirpation of the Prelacy that is exerciſed by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, their Chancellors, and Commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Deans, Deans and Chapters, Archdeacons, and all other Eccleſiaſtical Officers depending on that Hierarchy.</hi> And what is meant in both thoſe firſt Articles, by <hi>their ſincere, real, and conſtant Endeavours,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Worſhip and Government of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Churches, according to the Pattern of the <hi>Scottiſh,</hi> is plain from the laſt Article, wherein they Swear <hi>to aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that enter into the League and Covenant, in the maintaining and purſuing thereof; and that they ſhall not ſuffer themſelves di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly nor indirectly, by whatſoever Combination, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, or Terrour, to be divided from their Bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Conjunction, whether to make defection to the Contrary part, or to give themſelves to a deteſtable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency or Neutrality in the Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To paſs from the conſideration of the Covenant it ſelf, let us ſee what interpretation, in this point, is given upon it, by the Solemn Acts of their General Aſſemblies.</p>
            <p>That Aſſembly Convened at <hi>Glaſgow,</hi> in the year 1638.<note place="margin">Seſſ. 24. Decr. 6.</note> aſperſeth the Common Prayer of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with <hi>Popiſh Errors and Ceremonies, groſs Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition and Idolatry;</hi> ſcandalizeth their Book of Canons, <hi>for eſtabliſhing a tyrannical Power in the Biſhops;</hi> and condemns their Book of Conſecration, for ſettling Biſhops, and Preaching Deacons in the Church, <hi>contrary</hi> (as they falſly affirm) <hi>to the Word of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154141:4"/> God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 17. <hi>Decr.</hi> 10.</note> Again, in their Condemnation of the five Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Perth,</hi> for obſerving the Feſtivals of our Bleſſed Saviour, and his Holy Apoſtles, for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Baptiſm, Communion of the Sick, kneeling at the Scrament, and Confirmation; they inflict the Cenſures of the Church not only on thoſe that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them; but likewiſe on all thoſe that ſhall diſpute for any of theſe Things.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 8.19. Auguſt.</note>And a fortnight before the Covenant was autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in the year 1639. theſe three Books, and five Articles (but now mentioned) are rejected by the General Aſſembly then Convened at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> as the <hi>Cauſes of all the Evils of their Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, and when the Earl of <hi>Traquair,</hi> his Majeſty's Commiſſioner, read and gave in his Royal Maſters Declaration, that his <hi>Conſent to this their Act,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred no obligation to aboliſh the Epiſcopacy and the Liturgy in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and when he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to have this Declaration recorded among the Acts of their Church, the Moderator (in the Name of his Brethren) refuſed to grant Warrant for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 23. <hi>Aug.</hi> 30. 1639.</note> 
               <hi>as not agreeable with a good Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither is it ſtrange that the New-ſworn Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanters ſhould thus behave themſelves to that King's Commiſſioner, whoſe Declaration (read unto them in that very Seſſion) concerning his conſent to Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery in <hi>Scotland,</hi> expreſſed his Royal inclination for Biſhops and Liturgies, when the aboliſhing of both theſe in all the three Kingdoms, was ſo chiefly intended by their Oath, that on ſuch an Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhment
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154141:4"/> they Propheſied to themſelves that Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and</hi> England <hi>ſhould become one ſtick in the Hand of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aſſem. Anſwer to the Aſſem. at <hi>Weſtm. Aug. 29. 1643.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that it might come to paſs that the Lord's</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>in this Iſland ſhould be a City of trembling, and a burthenſome Stone to all their Enemies round about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> the I. in his incomparable Book,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 17.</note> confeſſeth, <hi>That ſo far reaſon of State did induce him, to approve the Government of the Church by Biſhops, above any other, as he found it impoſſible for a Prince to preſerve the State in quiet, unleſs he hath ſuch an influence upon Church-Men, and they ſuch a dependence on him, as may beſt reſtrain the Seditious Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances of Miniſters Tongues; who, with the Keys of Heaven, have ſo far the Keys of the Peoples Hearts, as they prevail much by their Oratory to let in or ſhut out both Peace and Loyalty.</hi> This made him repent that he had conſented to the taking away of Epiſcopacy in <hi>Scotland;</hi> and for this reaſon (among others) he would not condeſcend to take it away in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Presbyterians in their Zeal to promote this end of their League, <hi>In the Name of the Lord</hi> Jeſus,<note place="margin">Feb. 13. 1645.</note> 
               <hi>and in the Name of their whole National Church, which they repreſented, they made bold to warn his Majeſty freely, that the Guilt which cleav'd faſt to his Majesty and his Throne, was ſuch as, if not repented of, could not but involve himſelf and his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity under the Wrath of the everliving God, for his then reſiſting and oppoſing their Cauſe, which</hi> (in their Opinion) <hi>ſo much concerned the Glory of God. And if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154141:5"/> his Majeſty ſhould refuſe to hearken to their Counſel, they took God and Men to Witneſs, that they were blameleſs of the ſad Conſequences. In the mean time, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeched his Majeſty to take notice that they were not ſtaggering, or fainting, through the diffidence of the ſucceſs of their Cauſe, and Covenant of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this hope of ſucceſs of <hi>their Cauſe,</hi> to get Presbytery ſetled in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> according to the <hi>Covenant of the three Kingdoms;</hi> when the Duke of <hi>Hamilton</hi> engaged the Loyal Party in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for the preſervation of that King, <hi>Charles</hi> I. they remonſtrate againſt the <hi>Duke's Engagement,</hi> upon this very account, (among others of the ſame Nature,<note place="margin">Ult. July 1648.</note>) <hi>That in the Declaration for it, no mention was made concerning his then Majeſty's giving Security by his Solemn Oath, under his Name and Seal, that he ſhould for Himſelf, and his Succeſſors, give his Royal Aſſent for enjoyning</hi> Presbyterian Government <hi>in both Kingdoms, and that he ſhould never endeavour any change thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Remonſtrance againſt <hi>Duke Hamilton's Engagement,</hi> gave them the Name of <hi>Remonſtrators,</hi> when but a few among them were called <hi>Publick Reſolutioners,</hi> becauſe of their complying with the publick Reſolves of the Loyal Party: But leſt it ſhould not be a ſufficient fulfilment of the laſt Article of their Covenant againſt Neutrality in this Cauſe, that they make ſuch a <hi>Declaration</hi> to their Brethren at home;<note place="margin">Aug. 12. 1641.</note> they therefore ſend another (the very next day) to their Brethren here in <hi>England, That
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154141:5"/> when they conſidered what great expence of Blood and Pains theſe Kingdoms had been at for bringing their Work of Reformation to ſuch a length; and conſidering his then Majeſty's adhering to Epiſcopacy, they truſt that ſecurity would be demanded from his Majeſty, for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, before he ſhould be brought to one of his Houſes in or near about</hi> London, <hi>with Honour, Freedom, or Safety.</hi> And but ten days after this Declaration to the Covenanters here in <hi>England,</hi> they ſend a Letter to that King himſelf in which Letter (by them called their Humble Supplication,) they tell him,<note place="margin">Aug. 12. 1648.</note> 
               <hi>That it had been his Wiſdom in all that had befallen him, to read the righteous Hand of the Lord, writing bitter things againſt him, as for all his provocations; ſo eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for his having reſiſted their Work.</hi> And their Work which that bleſſed King <hi>reſiſted,</hi> was their ſettling of Presbytery in <hi>England;</hi> for which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, they (according to their Covenant) got him put to Death.</p>
            <p>Yea, after the Murder of this Royal Martyr, they in their Covenanted Zeal for Presbytery, here in <hi>England,</hi> declare to his Son, King <hi>Charles</hi> the II. that his adhering to Epiſcopacy,<note place="margin">Aug. 6. 1649.</note> and the Common Prayer, in the three Kingdoms, <hi>was nothing elſe but to oppoſe the Kingdom of the Son of God, and to Refuſe that Chriſt ſhould Reign over him and his Kingdoms, in his pure Ordinances of Church-Government and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus it does appear from the Covenant and Acts of Aſſemblies, that the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Covenanters are, by their Principles, obliged to introduce the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154141:6"/> Presbytery of <hi>Forty Eight</hi> into the Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond place, the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Covenanters are able at this time to put in practice thoſe Methods for introducing their Presbytery among us in <hi>England,</hi> which were proſecuted in the late times for that end. Acts and Letters, recorded in the Regiſters of the Aſſemblies of thoſe Days, make this evident, beyond diſpute; which for that purpoſe we ſhall at large ſet down.</p>
            <p>And firſt the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Covenanters may write in their Letter of Thanks to this King for their own Presbytery, their preſſing Remonſtrance to have it here among us; as well as their Forefathers writ it to King <hi>Charles</hi> I. under this Title:</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> And. 27. July. 1642.</note>To the King's moſt Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: The Hearty Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, and Humble Petition of the General Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>O<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R Hearts were filled with Joy and Gladneſs at the hearing of your Majeſty's Letter, which was read once and again in the Face of the Aſſembly; every Line almoſt expreſſing ſuch Affection to the Reformed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154141:6"/>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                     <hi>The King's expreſſion in his Letter is this,</hi> Where any thing is amiſs, we will endeavour a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in a fair and orderly way; and where Reformation is ſetled, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, with that Authority where with God hath veſted us, to maintain and defend it in Peace and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</note> Religion, and ſuch Royal care of us, as we could require from a Chriſtian Prince; or requiring ſo neceſſary Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties from us, as we are bound to perform as Minſters of the Goſpel, and Chriſtian Subjects; for which, as Solemn thanks were given by the Moderator of the Aſſembly, ſo do we all with one voice, in all Humility, preſent unto your Majeſty the thankfulneſs of our Hearts, with our earneſt Prayers unto God, for your Majeſty's Proſperity, and the Peace of your Kingdoms, that your Majeſty may be indeed a Nurſing Father to all the Kirks of Cbriſt in your Majeſty's Dominions, and eſpecially to the Kirk of <hi>Scotland;</hi> promiſing our moſt hearty En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, by Doctrine and Life, to advance the Goſpel of Chriſt, and to keep the People in our charge in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Peace, and in all Loyalty and Obedience to your Majeſty, and your Laws. Your Majeſty's Commands to your Commiſſioner to receive from us our juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable deſires, for what may further ſerve for the good of Religion here; the Favours which we have received already; and your Majeſty's deſire and delight to do Good, expreſſed in your Letters; are as many encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to us to take the boldneſs, in all Humility, to preſent unto your Majeſty, one thing, which for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is the chiefeſt of all our deſires, as ſerving moſt for the Glory of Chriſt, and that is, <hi>the Unity in Religion</hi> and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity in Church-Government; which we have preſſed as a Meen of a <hi>firm and durable Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Kingdoms;</hi> and without which, former experiences not only put us out of hope long to enjoy the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Goſpel with Peace; but have alſo rendred the Reaſons of our Hope and Confidence, as from other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154141:7"/> ſo from your Majeſty's late Letter to this Aſſembly, that you will be pleaſed to ſettle <hi>this Bleſſed Reformation.</hi> And therefore we your Majeſty's moſt loving Subjects, in the Name of whole Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> repreſented by us,<note n="(b)" place="margin">It's ſtrange that any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who pray to an earthly Prince upon the Knees of their Hearts, will not bow the Knees of their Bodies in their Prayers at the Sacrament.</note> upon the Knees of our Hearts, do moſt humbly and earneſtly beg, That your Majeſty in the depth of your Royal Wiſdom, and from your affection to the True Religion, and the Peace of your Kingdoms, may be moved to conſider, that the God of Heaven and Earth is calling for <hi>this Reformation</hi> at your Hands; and that as you are his Vicegerent, ſo you may be his prime Inſtrument in it. If it ſhall pleaſe the Lord (which is our deſire and hope) that this Bleſſed <hi>Unity in Religion, and Uniformity in Government</hi> ſhall be brought about, your Majeſty's Conſcience, in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſo great <hi>a duty,</hi> ſhall be a well-ſpring of Comfort to your ſelf, your Memory ſhall be a ſweet ſavour, and your Name renowned to all following Generations; and if the unhappy Commotions and Diviſions ſhall end in this Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, then it ſhall appear in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, they were but the noiſe of many Waters, and the voice of a great Thunder before the voice of Harpers, harping with their Harps, which ſhall fill the whole Iſland with Melody and Mirth, and the Name of it ſhall be, <hi>The Lord is there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is the exact tranſcript of that Aſſembly's Supplication to King</hi> Charles <hi>the I. only that for Brevity ſome Perſonal things relating to his then Majeſty, and the then Parliaments Declaration are omitted becauſe they do not quadrat with the times.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:154141:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the ſecond place, the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Covenanters keep the ſame correſpondence with their Brethren here, as was kept in the days of their Forefathers: And accordingly (as was done in the late times) grant to this effect, and in this manner:</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="commission">
               <head>A Commiſſion for thoſe that repair to the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Edinb. Aug. 19. 1643.</note>
               </head>
               <p>THE General Aſſembly of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> finding it neceſſary to ſend ſome Godly and Learned of this Kirk to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> to the effect underwritten. Therefore gives full Power and Commiſſion to Mr. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">For in this Conſiſtory the Mis. <hi>John</hi> that is Miniſter, hath the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence to his Grace the Duke, who is a Ruling Elder, or but a Laick join'd in Council.</note> Miniſters, and to <hi>D. M. E.</hi> or <hi>L.</hi> Elders, or any three of them, whereof two ſhall be Miniſters, to repair to the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> and there to deliver the Declaration ſent unto the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England,</hi> and the Letter ſent unto the Aſſembly of Divines now ſitting in that Kingdom. And to propoſe, conſult, treat and conclude with that Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, or any Commiſſioners deputed by them, or any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees or Commiſſioners deputed by the Houſes of Parliament, in all Matters which may further the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of this Iſland, <hi>in one Form of Kirk-Government,</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:154141:8"/> one<note n="(b)" place="margin">And tho' the <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> Confeſſ. avows the K's. Supremacy, which they do not own, yet they have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen it in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance with <hi>England.</hi>
                  </note> Confeſſion of Faith, one Catechiſm, and one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory for the Worſhip of God, according to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which they have received from the Aſſembly, or ſhall receive from time to time hereafter, from the<note n="(c)" place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the Kirk, is the great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the General Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, which does all affairs when the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly does not ſit.</note> Commiſſioners of the Aſſembly deputed for that effect: With power alſo to them, to convey to His Majeſty the humble anſwer ſent from this Aſſembly to His Majeſties Letter, by ſuch occaſion as they ſhall think convenient, and generally Authorizeth them to do all things which may further the ſo much deſired <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, and neareſt Conjunction of the Churches of <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> conform to their Inſtructions before-mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And if our Presbyterians here in</hi> England, <hi>ſhould entertain the correſpondence ſo far, as to Petition in any Letter, the concurrence of their Covenanted Brethren in</hi> Scotland, <hi>then, in that caſe, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably will return ſuch an anſwer, as was return'd to our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Presbyterians by the</hi> Scottiſh, <hi>in the year 1642. Dated at St.</hi> Andrews, July <hi>22.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Right Reverend and Beloved in the Lord Jeſus.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>YOur Letters which came unto our Hands ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonably, was not only acceptable unto us, but hath alſo encouraged us to renew, both to the Kings
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154141:8"/> Majeſty, and the Houſes<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                           <hi>In their Declaration to the Houſes of Parliament,</hi> Who knows <hi>(ſay they)</hi> but the Lord hath now ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie with <hi>England,</hi> which will not be removed, till firſt, and before all, the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of his Name, and the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Houſe be ſettled accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own Will <hi>(meaning to have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhop nor Common Prayer.)</hi>
                        </note> of Parliament, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Commiſſioners of this Kingdom for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Religion. We cannot be ignorant, but the oppoſition from Satan and Worldly Men, in Kirk and Policy, will ſtill be vehement as it hath been already, but we are confident, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that the prayers and endeavours of the Godly of both Kingdoms, will bring the Work to a wiſhed and bleſſed iſſue. This whole National Kirk is ſo much concern'd in that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and <hi>Unity in Religion</hi> in both Kingdoms, that without it we cannot hope, for any long time, to enjoy our Purity and Peace, which hath cost us ſo dear, and is now our chiefeſt Comfort, and greateſt Treaſure; which one cauſe (beſide the Honour of God, and the Happineſs of the People of God in that Kingdom) <hi>more deſired of us than our lives</hi>) is more than ſufficient to move us to contribute all that is in our power, for bringing it to paſs. And ſince we have with ſo great liberty made our deſires and hopes known, both to King and Parliament, it is a duty incumbent both to you and us, who make mention of the Lord, and are Watchmen upon the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> never more to keep ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, nor to hold our peace Day and Night, till the Righteouſneſs of <hi>Zion</hi> go forth as brightneſs, and the Salvation thereof as a Lamp that burneth. And if it ſhall pleaſe the Lord to move the heart of King and Parliament, to hearken unto the motion, for which end we have reſolved to keep a Solemn Faſt and Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in all the Kirks of this Kingdom (the mean by which we have prevailed in times paſt) we wiſh that the Work may be begun with ſpeed, and proſecuted
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154141:9"/> with diligence, by the joynt Labours of ſome Divines in both Kingdoms, who may prepare the ſame for the view and examination of a more frequent Eccleſiaſtical meeting of the best affected to this Reformation there, and of the Commiſſioners of the General Aſſembly here, that in the end, it may have the Approbation of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly here, and of all the Kirks there, in the beſt way that may be, we wiſh and hope, at laſt, in a National Aſſembly. Our Commiſſioners at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> ſhall in our Name, receive and return Anſwers, for promoting ſo great a Work; which we, with our Heart, and our Soul, recommend to the bleſſing of God. We continue,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Loving Brethren, and Fellow Labourers.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And although the Oath of Supremacy be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Presbytery, and hath been taken by many in this Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> of all degrees and ſtations, yet the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Covenanters, for curing that diſtemper of Malignancy, may Inſtitute a Faſt, of the ſame nature, and for the ſame cauſes, as made their Predeceſſors do it in the 6th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1642.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154141:9"/>
               <head>Act for remembring in Publick Prayers the deſires of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly to the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and induction of a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faſt.</head>
               <p>THE General Aſſembly being deſirous to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the great Work of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Religion, and <hi>Uniformity in Church Government,</hi> in all theſe three Dominions, for which the Aſſembly hath humbly ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated the Kings Majesty, and remonſtrated their deſires to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> leſt they ſhould be wanting in any mean that may Advance <hi>ſo Glorious</hi> and ſo Good a Work, do Ordain, That not only the ſaid Declaration to the Parliament, and Supplication to the Kings Majeſty, ſhall be accompanied with the earneſt Petitions and Prayers of the whole Brethren, in private and publick, for the Lords bleſſing thereunto, according to the laudable cuſtom of our Predeceſſors, who in the year of God <hi>1589,</hi> Ordains that the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, in their private and publick Prayers, recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto God the eſtate of the afflicted ſtate of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</hi> But having juſt cauſe of fear, that the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of the Land, which ſo much abound, may hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this ſo great a Work, do alſo Ordain a Solemn Faſt,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154141:10"/> to be kept on tht Second<note n="(a)" place="margin">For they can Faſt on a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny day of the Week but on <hi>Friday;</hi> yea, tho' it were <hi>Good Friday,</hi> in Paſſion Week, they moſt then make their <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and <hi>Eaſter</hi> Dinner, in one, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Lords Day of <hi>September,</hi> for the Cauſes after ſpecified.</p>
               <p>Groſs Ignorance, and all ſorts of Wickedneſs amongſt the greater part; Security, meer Formality and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſs among the beſt, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nthankfulneſs in all.</p>
               <p>The Sword raging throughout all <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> but moſt Barbarouſly in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and daily more and more threatned in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That God may Graciouſly bleſs the Supplication of the Aſſembly to the Kings Majeſty, and their Propoſals to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Religion, and <hi>Uniformity in Church Government,</hi> and<note n="(b)" place="margin">And ſome of thoſe means were the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt K. <hi>Ch.</hi> I.</note> all other means which may ſerve for the promoting of ſo great a Work, and the advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt every where.</p>
               <p>That God may powerfully overturn all Wicked Plots and Deſigns of<note n="(c)" place="margin">For in the Divinity of theſe Saints, every Biſhop is a limb of Antichriſt.</note> Antichriſt, and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and all diviſive Propoſals againſt the courſe of Reformation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And ſince the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Teſt hath produced in the Minds of all their Nobility, Gentry, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial part of their Commons (out of the Five</hi> Weſtern <hi>Shires) mighty averſion to ſuch a Faſt, yet the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Covenanters, for having the more unanimous Concurrence among themſelves, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154141:10"/> Presbytery among us again, they may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new their Solemn League, as it was for the ſame effect renewed by the Aſſembly at</hi> Edinburgh.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acts">
               <head>
                  <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 6. Auguſt 8. 1642. Acts for Subſcribing the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</head>
               <p>THE General Aſſembly conſidering the good and pious Advice of the Commiſſioners of the laſt Aſſembly, upon the 22d of <hi>September,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">This is their Covenant with the Lord, which ſhall never be forgotten. <hi>Gen. Aſſem.</hi> Edenb. Aug. <hi>19. 1643.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>poſt meridiem,</hi> recommending to Presbyteries to have Copies of the Covenant, to be ſubſcribed by every Miniſter at his Admiſſion; doth therefore ratifie and approve the ſame. And further Ordains, That the Covenant be Reprinted, with the Ordinance prefixed thereto; and that every Synod, Presbytery and Pariſh, have one of them bound in <hi>Quarto,</hi> with ſome blank Paper, whereupon every Perſon may be obliged to Subſcribe: And that the Covenants of the Synod and Presbytery, be keeped by their Moderators <hi>Reſpective;</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:154141:11"/> of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities by their Principals, of Pariſhes by their Miniſters, with all carefulneſs: And that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account of Obedience to this Act be required hereafter, in all Viſitations of Pariſhes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, and Presbyteries, in all Tryals of Presbyteries, and Synods Book's.</p>
               <p>The General Aſſembly conſidering that the Act of Aſſembly at <hi>Edinburgh 1639. Auguſt 30.</hi> injoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Perſons to Subſcribe the Covenant, under all Eccleſiaſtical Cenſure, hath not been obeyed; therefore ordains all Miniſters, to make intimation of the ſaid Act in their Churches, and thereafter to proceed, with Cenſures of the Church, againſt ſuch as ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to Subſcribe the Covenant. And that exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count be taken of every Miniſters diligence herein, by their Presbyteries and Synods, as they will anſwer to their General Aſſembly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And if after the renewing of the Covenant, the Men of Honour and Conſcience will yet avoid the taking it, then in that caſe, the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Covenanters may (as their Forefathers 1644. did before them) get another Act paſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="act">
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:154141:11"/>
                  <head>Againſt ſecret Diſaffecters of the Covenant.</head>
                  <p>THE General Aſſembly underſtanding that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Perſons,<note place="margin">Judge from this Act, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and the Fanatick In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitions.</note> diſaffected to the Solemn League and Covenant, of the three Kingdoms, do eſcape their Juſt Cenſure, either by their private and unconſtant abode, in any one Congregation, or by ſecret convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their Malignant Speeches and Practices, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Ordains all Miniſters to take ſpecial notice, when any ſuch Perſon ſhall come within their Pariſhes, and ſo ſoon as they ſhall know the ſame, that without delay they cauſe warn them to appear before the Presbyteries, within which their Pariſhes lyes, or before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of this Aſſembly, appointed for publick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, as they ſhall find moſt convenient; which warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Aſſembly declares ſhall be a ſufficient Citation unto them. And in like manner, that all Miniſters and Lay-elders, inform the ſaid <hi>Judicatories Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective</hi> againſt every ſuch diſaffected Perſon, altho' without their own Pariſh, ſo ſoon as they ſhall hear of them. And the Aſſembly Ordains the ſaid Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, not only to proceed to Tryal and Cenſure of ſuch diſaffected Perſons, but alſo to take a ſpecial account of the diligence of Miniſters, Ruling-elders, and Presbyteries, herein <hi>Reſpective.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154141:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After the Covenant is thus renewed, and ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſly enjoyn'd, matters at length are ripe for the Uniformity betwixt both Kingdoms in Church Government and Worſhip; and therefore, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Example given to them 1645, the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Covenanters may give out their</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="act">
                  <head>Solemn and Seaſonable Warning to the Noblemen, Barons, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Burroughs, Miniſters and Commons of <hi>Scotland;</hi> as alſo to their Armies without, and within the Kingdom.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Warning was dated 12</hi> Feb. Poſt meridiem, Seſſ. <hi>18. and becauſe it takes up two Sheets and an half, in the Book of the Acts of their General Aſſemblies, and is therefore too long to be here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted</hi> verbatim, <hi>therefore (in their own Words) you may take its ſubſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>AS for our part, our Forces ſent unto that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <hi>(meaning England)</hi> in purſuance of the Covenant, have been ſo<note n="(a)" place="margin">In defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of K. <hi>Ch.</hi> the Firſt, one commanded by the M. of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> the other by P. <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert.</hi>
                     </note> mercifully and manifeſtly aſſiſted and bleſſed from Heaven, that we have what
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154141:12"/> to anſwer the Enemy that reproacheth us concerning that buſineſs, and that which may make Iniquity her ſelf to ſtop her mouth. But which is more unto us than all Victories, or whatever Temporal Bleſſing, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Religion in<note n="(b)" place="margin">Here is plain Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and home to the purpoſe.</note> 
                     <hi>England,</hi> and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity therein betwixt both Kingdoms (a principal end of the Covenant) is ſo far advanced, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Service-Book, with the<note n="(c)" place="margin">Eſpecially <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> which they condemn'd as Superſtitious, by their Act of the very next day after this warning was given, 13 <hi>Feb.</hi> 1645.</note> Holy Days, and many other Ceremonies contained in it; together with the Prelacy, the Fountain of all theſe, are aboliſhed and taken away. In this we rejoice, and will rejoice, that the Lord Jeſus Chriſt is no loſer, but a Conquerour; that his Ordinances take place, that his Cauſe prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the Work of his Purging and Building the Temple goeth forward, and not backward. But beſides the defection of many of this Nation, under our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, from our firſt National Covenant (a ſin not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by God, if not repented of by Men as well as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken) our later Vows and Covenants have been alſo foully violated, by not contributing our uttermoſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to this Cauſe, with our Eſtates and Lives, and by not endeavouring with all faithfulneſs, the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, tryal, and deſerved puniſhment of all Malignants. The duties of Humiliation, Repentance, Faith, Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though the principal, yet are not all which are required at the hands of this Nation. But let all ſorts of people, both high and low, in this Kingdom, call to mind the Solemn Covenants, and pay their Vows unto the moſt high; and namely, that Article of our<note n="(d)" place="margin">By the firſt Covenant they mean that call'd the National Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and which was fram'd in K. <hi>James</hi> VI. Reign. And by the ſecond Covenant, they mean their ſolemn League, which was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triv'd for that one Nation, as the firſt was, but for all the three Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Kingdoms.</note> firſt Covenant, which obligeth us not to impede nor hinder any ſuch Reſolution, as by common conſent ſhall
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154141:13"/> be found to conduce for the ends of the Covenant. In our laſt Covenant, there is another Article which we wiſh may be well remember'd at this time, namely, That we ſhall aſſiſt and defend all that enter unto this League and Covenant, in the maintaining and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing thereof, and ſhall not ſuffer our ſelves, directly or indirectly, by whatſoever combination, perſwaſion, or terrour, to be divided or withdrawn from this bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Conjunction, whether to make defection to the contrary part, or to give our ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency, or neutrality in this Cauſe; according to which Article, Mens reality and integrity in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant will be manifeſt and demonſtrable, as well by their Omiſſions, as by their Commiſſions. Whoever he be that will not adventure his Perſon, or put out thoſe who are under his power, or pay Contributions for the maintenance of the Forces, muſt be taken for a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant and Covenant-breaker, and ſo involved both in the diſpleaſure of God, and Cenſures of the Kirk.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After this Solemn warning is given by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters of</hi> Scotland, <hi>that it may have the better effect towards the overthrow of our Epiſcopacy, and the aboliſhing of our Common Prayer in</hi> England, <hi>they may, after the example of the Men of Forty Eight, get an</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="act">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:154141:13"/>
                  <head>Act for Cenſuring Miniſters for their Silence, and not ſpeaking againſt the Corruptions of the Time.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THeir Act of this Title was made in the General Aſſembly, of the year 1648, at</hi> Edenburgh, <hi>3</hi> Aug. ante me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rediem, Seſſ. <hi>26. And it particularly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains,</hi> That the main currrent of Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in Sermons may run alone, againſt the Evils that prevail at home; and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, againſt the defection from the League and Covenant; againſt the unlawful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement in War,<note n="(a)" place="margin">And by their Act <hi>July</hi> 28. 1648. all Decrees even of Parliament are unjuſt, if eſtabliſhed without their conſent, when they concern the common Cant of the Covenant.</note> and unjuſt Decrees Eſtabliſhed by Law, and againſt the Plots and Practices of Malignants. <hi>And in the concluſion of this Act, they Ordain, That</hi> in caſe any Miniſter for his freedom of Preaching, ſhall be in the face of the Congregation, or elſewhere, upbraided, rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154141:14"/> at, mocked or threatned, the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery of the Bounds, ſhall immediately pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue the Offendor; and whoever he be, charge him to ſatisfie the Diſcipline of the Church by publick Repentance, which if they do not, or refuſe to do, that then the Presbytery proceed to Excommunication againſt him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And when the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Covenanters have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded thus, out of Zeal for Uniformity of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery in both Kingdoms, in imitation of what was done by their Predeceſſors, they can ſhew their Zeal in</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="exhortation">
                  <head>A Brotherly Exhortation from the General Aſſembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to their Brethren in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis Exhortation of their Predeceſſors was dated <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1649, <hi>Seſſ. ult.</hi> And paſſing over the Preface thereof, which conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Troubles which then oppreſt theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154141:14"/> as Gods Judgments for the breach of their Covenant, for Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi>'s Engagement for his Royal Maſters Service, and for the<note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Which in their Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion 20</hi> Aug. <hi>1647. they call</hi> A Liberty of Errour, Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, Schiſm, Hereſie, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring God, oppoſing the Truth, hindring Reformation, and ſeducing others.</note> Liberty of Conſcience to Proteſtant Diſſenters: And paſſing over, that in all theſe Troubles, the thing which griev'd them moſt (to ſpeak in their own Words) was, <hi>That there was Interruption in the building of the Lords Houſe in</hi> England: And paſſing over their Reproof to the Covenant-breakers, and their high Commendation of thoſe who kept it, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to them here in <hi>England</hi> is in the laſt Paragraph <hi>verbatim.</hi> Thus,</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>As we ſhall ever (God willing) be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of our Duty to the faithful that adhere to the Covenant in <hi>England,</hi> having them always in our Hearts before the Lord, ſo we deſire to be refreſhed with their Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Boldneſs in the Cauſe of God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their places. This is the time of their Tryal, and the hour of Temptation among them; bleſſed ſhall they be who ſhall be found following the Lamb, and ſhall not be aſhamed of his Teſtimony. We know in ſuch dark Hours, many are drawn away with the multitude, when the Lord will again Purge and make White; and we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154141:15"/> doubt not but many ſuch are in <hi>England,</hi> whom the bold and clear Preaching of Chriſt may reclaim; much therefore lyeth upon the Watchmen at this time, that their Trumpet may give a certain and diſtinct ſound, warning and exhorting every one, as thoſe that muſt give account, and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall thoſe Servants be, who ſhall be found faithful in their Lords Houſe, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to his Houſhold what is meet for this Seaſon, and can ſay they are free from the Blood of all Men, having ſhewn them the whole Counſel of God, being in nothing terrified of the threats of their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; and bleſſed and happy ſhall that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be, that walk in the Light, holden forth by them, and ſtay upon the Lord in this dark time, hearkning to the voice of his Servants, and walking in the light of his Word, and not in the ſparks of their own, which will end in ſorrow. How unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable will <hi>England</hi> be, having ſo foully Revolted againſt ſo many fair Teſtimonies, which the Lord Chriſt hath entred as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154141:15"/> to preſerve his Right, in theſe ends of the Earth, long ſince given unto him for his poſſeſſion, and of late confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Solemn Covenant. Chriſts Right to theſe Kingdoms, is ſurer than that he ſhould be pleaded out of it by pretended Liberty of Conſcience, and his begun poſſeſſion is more precious to him, than to be ſatisfied with a <hi>diſhonourable Toleration.</hi> All that yet we have ſeen, doth not weaken our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the Lords Glorifying the Houſe of his Glory in theſe Lands, and of his Sons taking unto him his great power, and reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the beauty and power of his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in this Iſland. His Name is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful and ſo alſo his Works, we ought not therefore to ſquare them according to our line, but leave them to him who hath the Government laid upon his Shoulder, all whoſe ways are Judgment, and whoſe ruling theſe Kingdoms had never yet reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline. It is good for us to be ſtedfaſt in our Duty, and therein quietly to wait and hope for the Salvation of God. The word of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154141:16"/> promiſe is ſure, and hath an appointed time, that he that will come ſhall come, and will not tarry. There is none hath cauſe to diſtruſt the Lords Word to his People. It hath often to our Experience been tryed in the Fire, and hath ever come forth with a more Glorious luſtre. Let not therefore theſe that ſuffer in <hi>England</hi> caſt away their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, they are not the firſt who have need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed patience after that they had done the Lords Will. But let them ſtrengthen the weak hands, and confirm the feeble knees, and ſay to the fearful in heart, Be ſtrong, fear not, behold your God will come with Vengeance, even God with a recompence, he will come and ſave you. Now the Juſt ſhall live by Faith, whereas thoſe that draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth back, or becometh luke-warm in the Lords work, his ſoul ſhall abhor them, and he ſhall ſpew them out of his mouth. But we perſwade our ſelves of better things of theſe our brethren in <hi>England;</hi> and prayeth that the God of peace, who brought again from the dead our Lord Jeſus, that great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154141:16"/> Shepherd of the Sheep, through the blood of the everlaſting Covenant, may make them perfect in every good work to do his will, working in them that which is well-pleaſing in his ſight through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom be glory for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Theſe are the Methods taken by the Fathers, which the Children of the Covenant may uſe at this time for introducing (a ſecond time) their Presbytery among us. They may Petition the King that now is, for Uniformity in Church-Government in all the three Kingdoms. They may ſend up to our Diſſenters in <hi>England,</hi> ſome Commiſſioned to treat for that effect. They may encourage our Diſſenters, with their Letters, promiſing aſſiſtance in that common concern. They may appoint a Publick Faſt to amuſe the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with the apprehenſions of Piety in the Work. After that, they may have the Covenant renewed, and diſaffecters of that Oath puniſhable. Then they may give out their warning to all ſorts of people among them, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Neutrality, in the proſecution of this part of the Covenant. Then Miniſters for ſilence at this Neutrality may be inflicted with Cenſure. And after all, their Brethren in <hi>England</hi> may be exhorted to Zeal, and againſt Toleration. And therefore nothing is wanted to repreſent the danger
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154141:17"/> of our Church of <hi>England,</hi> from the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters; but to demonſtrate in the concluſion, That as they are obliged by their Principles and Oaths to ruine her, and as they are able to follow (for that effect) the Methods which their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors took, ſo they are willing to do it.</p>
                  <p>In the third place, That the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are willing to ruin this Church of <hi>England</hi> (by the ſame methods) is evident from their practices in theſe three laſt years. For they who from a Zeal for the Covenant, ſo early petitioned the King for Presbytery in <hi>Scotland,</hi> will for the preſervation thereof addreſs to him again, that it may be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> They who after Sermons in their publick meetings uſe to ſend up prayers to God, <hi>that the work which they have begun in Covenanted</hi> Scotland <hi>may be perfected in the other two Kingdoms;</hi> will not ſail to ſend up Commiſſioners hither for that effect. They who laſt year procured from the Eſtates of that Kingdom aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, thanks to the Rabble whom they themſelves had hunted out, againſt many faithful Miniſters; will not fail this year to promiſe their aſſiſtance to the Diſſenters here. They who have already kept a faſt in <hi>Scotland</hi> for their <hi>falling from their firſt Love</hi> (meaning their Love of Presbytery) will certainly inſtitute another at this time, that the King and this Kingdom may fall in Love with it too. They who have refuſed to baptize children when their Parents refuſed to abjure the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Teſt (becauſe that ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jures the Covenant) cannot but renew the ſolemn
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154141:17"/> League, and perſecute thoſe who diſaffect it. And they whoſe Doctrine hath been theſe two laſt years that the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation hath not (under Biſhops) heard the Goſpel theſe 28 years; will not fail to exhort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Neutrality of Covenanters, and to cenſure thus their Miniſters who do not Preach againſt ſuch Defection. And after all, they who have already excited the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Zealots of this Kingdom to affront the firſt Peereſs of their Nation, for inviting her late Epiſcopal Paſtor to Preach in her Graces Palace, (when ſome of their own number had declined to do it) are certainly averſe from all Toleration, even to peaceable Proteſtant Diſſenters.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154141:18"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154141:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
